Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection
1990-1991
AIA.012
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.25 linear feet in 1 manuscript box and 4 media boxes
This collection consists of 34 interviews conducted by Jane Conlon Muller with civil rights lawyer and politician Paul O’Dwyer, Irish Northern Aid founder Michael Flannery, and Kings County District Attorney Charles J. Hynes. The interviews were produced as part of an oral history project with the New York Irish History Roundtable and document numerous aspects of Irish American studies and the immigrant experience in America, with specific emphasis on New York. Subjects include the interviewees childhoods and family lives, their professional and political activities, and their involvement with various Irish American movements or organizations, including civil rights and hunger strikes in Northern Ireland and providing support to the families of killed or imprisoned IRA soldiers.
Muller, Jane Conlon.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Archival Materials
Related collections at Tamiment Library include:
Frank Durkan Papers (AIA 008)
Irish Republicanism Collection (AIA 022)
Ireland House Oral History Collection (AIA 030)
Paul O’Dwyer’s personal and official papers are housed at St. John’s University, Jamaica, New York and at the Municipal Archives, 31 Chambers Street, New York City. An oral history conducted with him in 1962 is preserved in Box 20 at Columbia University’s Oral History Research Office, Room 801 Butler Library, New York City.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of 34 interviews conducted by Jane Conlon Muller with three interview subjects: Paul O’Dwyer, Michael Flannery, and Charles J. Hynes. In the 22 interviews with O’Dwyer, he discusses numerous historically significant moments and movements he participated in, including educating African Americans about voting in Mississippi during the 1960s, presiding over the New York City Council, and the 1968 Democratic National Convention. His interviews document many aspects of Irish American studies, immigrant experiences in America, his legal career, and his political experiences, including running for various offices, the development of the McBride Principles, and the civil rights movement in Northern Ireland. The two interviews with Michael Flannery focus on his experiences in Ireland during the War for Independence and the Irish Civil War and his later life in the United States, including the founding of and resigning from Noraid. The interview with Charles J. Hynes concerns his childhood, family, and his involvement in Irish American affairs, beginning with the 1981 hunger strikes in Northern Ireland.
Arrangement
Original interview recordings are numbered 1-34 and arranged into three series by interviewee:
I. Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998)
II. Michael Flannery (1902-1994)
III. Charles J. Hynes (1935- )
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to preservation concerns, all researchers interested in using Tamiment Library’s audiovisual materials must use an access copy, which can be requested in our reading room. Our ability to create reproductions of audiovisual materials for off-site personal research use is dependent on a copyright assessment and requires a reproduction fee.
To request the use of audiovisual materials, for off-site personal research, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested and a librarian will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Jane Conlon Muller in 1991 and 2000.
Historical/Biographical Note
The interviews in this collection were conducted in 1990 and 1991 by Jane Conlon Muller, an attorney and member of the New York Irish History Roundtable. She first interviewed O'Dwyer, who suggested that she also interview Flannery. At this time, Muller worked in the Kings County DA's office, which was the impetus for interviewing Hynes. Jane Conlon Muller, born in 1942, is the granddaughter of Irish immigrants from counties Donegal, Leitrim and Clare. She holds a bachelors degree from Queens College and a Juris Doctorate from CUNY Law School. After leaving the Kings County DA's office, she opened her own law practice, which specializes in construction law, elder law, wills, trusts and estates as well as real estate.
American Congress for Irish Freedom.; Clan-na-Gael.; Flannery, Michael, 1902-1994; Gaelic Athletic Association.; Hynes, Charles J., 1935-; Irish Action Committee.; Irish Republican Army.; Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association.; New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee.; O'Dwyer, Paul, 1907-; United Irish Counties Association.; Ireland |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Lawyers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Revolutionaries |z Ireland.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements.
- Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998), 1990-1991; 29 cassettes, 29 master compact discs, 29 access compact discs
  Scope and Contents note
  The 22 interviews with O'Dwyer were conducted between February 1990 and May 1991 in his office at the United Nations building in Manhattan. He viewed these oral histories as a sort of continuation of his autobiography, Counsel for the Defense, which was published in 1979. Although he discusses some of the issues also touched on in his book, such as educating African-Americans about voting in Mississippi during the 1960s, presiding over the New York City Council, and his participation in the 1968 Democratic National Convention, O'Dwyer also discusses his experiences both in Ireland and in America since writing the book.
  The interviews contain much information relevant to Irish American studies, including insights into the history of Irish immigration and experiences in America especially in New York; the New York St. Patrick's Day parade; and Irish American athletics, radio shows, and newspapers. O'Dwyer recounts his experiences as a politician in the U.S., including running for various offices, the development and success of the McBride Principles, his relationship to the Jewish community in New York, his relationship with New York Senator Daniel Moynihan, and his work with the United Nations. He also discusses his experiences as a lawyer, including his involvement with professional organizations, such as the National Lawyers Guild and the Brehon Law Society and specific cases he worked on, such as the Fort Worth Five and Joe Doherty.
  O'Dwyer also discusses Ireland - the history of the discontent between Catholics and Protestants in the North, the civil rights movement, the 1981 hunger strikes, Irish travelers, and the development of the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home and O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation.
  Historical/Biographical Note
  Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998), born in Lismirrane, Parish of Bohola, County Mayo, Ireland, was a politician and lawyer noted for his dedication to civil rights. Arriving in the U.S. in 1925, O'Dwyer enrolled in St. John's Law School the following year and graduated in 1931. In 1932, he joined the law firm O'Dwyer and Bernstein. He began his career defending pickets against labor-organizing injunctions, opposing the deportation of foreign-born agitators, and defending the rights of unionists to organize. He was a member of the National Lawyers Guild and served as president of the New York chapter in 1947.
  O'Dwyer gained success in the courtroom, participating in numerous civil rights struggles in America during the second half of the twentieth century. He worked at registration drives for African Americans in Mississippi during the 1960s, defended Communists and Communist sympathizers during the McCarthy era, vigorously protested the Vietnam War, and battled for the foundation of the state of Israel.
  O'Dwyer participated in politics both by working behind the scenes on other candidates' campaigns and by running his own campaigns. He assisted in John F. Kennedy's 1962 presidential campaign and David Dinkins' 1998 mayoral campaign. O'Dwyer's own campaigns were less successful. Out of a dozen electoral efforts, he lost all but two: the 1963 race for councilman-at-large in Manhattan and the 1973 race for City Council President.
  O'Dwyer managed to maintain his identity as an Irish nationalist and embrace his role as an Irish American. The quest for a united Ireland remained a high priority and during his frequent visits back to Ireland he met with all sides of the conflict, including the Irish Republican Army, the Ulster Defense Association, and the Irish government. He introduced the McBride Principles to the United States government, which prevent U.S. government agencies from investing in Northern Ireland companies that discriminate against their employees. He transformed his childhood home into the O'Dwyer-Cheshire Home for Disabled Children and Adults and established the O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation, both to fund the Cheshire home in the future, and also in an effort to reforest part of Ireland.
  In addition to his civil rights work in the U.S., O'Dwyer was involved in many Irish American organizations, including the United Irish Counties Association, the Mayo Men's Patriotic and Benevolent Association, the New York St. Patrick's Day Parade Committee, and the Gaelic Athletic Association. His love for New York City and its history led him to assist in the creation of the Department of Records and Information Services (D.O.R.I.S.) to oversee the Municipal Archives and to become the Manhattan Borough Historian in 1986. He was the founder in 1950 of the philanthropic Irish Institute of New York, Inc.
  In 1990 O'Dwyer was appointed the New York City Commissioner to the United Nations and Consular Corps. In this capacity he was instrumental in having the Brehon Law Society admitted to the UN as a non-governmental organization.
  After a series of small strokes, O'Dwyer retired to his home in Goshen, New York where he died on June 12, 1998.
  Sources:
  Glazier, Michael, ed. The Encyclopedia of the Irish in America. Notre Dame: University of Notre Dame Press, 1999.
  O'Dwyer, Paul. Counsel for the Defense: The Autobiography of Paul O'Dwyer. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1979.
  Rohan, Brian. "Paul O'Dwyer, 90, Remembered as a Hero." Irish Voice. 7 July 1998, 3.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc; [00:00 - 10:00] Paul O'Dwyer introduced. O'Dwyer's hopes to create an informal hearing to gather information about the reasons (or excuses) the United States used to invade Panama in 1989. Discussion about how Americans allow the government to get away with things by remaining silent on important issues as seen with President Reagan in Grenada and President Bush in Panama. [10:00 - 20:00] Participation in Mayor Dinkins' election. Involvement in other civil rights oriented elections, including electing an African American man to be the mayor of Sunflower, Mississippi. Civil rights cases in the South, including a case in Jackson, Mississippi where he represented a black man who lost his job and whose house was firebombed because he tried to register to vote. Judge's official opinion that African Americans are less intelligent than whites because their heads are smaller.Dangers of working in the South during the civil rights movement and the precautions he took, such as never riding in a car with an African American person.Work with the Freedom Democratic party on the campaign of Victoria Gray, an African American candidate for Congress. [20:00 - end] Work with Eleanor Owens Jackson, a professor of law at Georgetown University Law School. Jackson was in charge of COPAL(?), an amalgam of civil rights organizations including the National Lawyers Guild, of which O'Dwyer was a member. O'Dwyer's job was to go to African-American churches and educate them about voting. He tells of his experiences on that job, such as teaching young African Americans how to stay within the regulations for voting.Case of Lois Chaffee, a white teacher at Tougaloo College, who was arrested for disorderly conduct after police found her with African Americans after a protest march through Jackson, MI. (Box 4, Cd 1, Track 1, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 1)
    [05:48] How far along have you gotten with forming this committee?
    [06:33] Do you have any idea at all why you think there was no opposition that you mentioned before?
    [08:15] Have you anyone on your committee that's been in Panama recently?
    [08:35] So you have a fact gathering committee in effect?
    [10:52] What state was that?
    [14:18] May I ask you what year this was?
    [17:25] Was this before or after that incident? When you were down there and you tried this case?
    [17:44] You took certain precautions that you've mentioned - what was your state of mind at that time when you were down there?
    [19:11] What office was she running for?
    [20:28] You constantly refer to 'we,' so you obviously weren't there by yourself. Could you tell us who else was a part of your group?
    [22:14] She graduated from where?
    [23:35] Was it just that they [African Americans] were inexperienced in voting or were they also afraid?
    [24:32] Am I to understand then that you went down at different times during the sixties and for certain lengths of times? 2 weeks? 3 weeks? Longer?
    [25:52] This was a somewhat organized movement then that you were a part of?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Chaffey case and difficulty finding a Mississippi lawyer. O'Dwyer brought an action against the mayor and governor and made them testify in this case to show how corrupt the establishment was and how it was depriving people of their rights.Another case concerning letting an African American woman use the public library where the courts ruled that she was allowed to use it, but no other African Americans could. [10:00 - 20:00] Discusses role of Catholic church in civil rights movement in Mississippi. Conversation with liberal local parish priest and his perspective on the civil rights movement. More on priests in Mississippi and their activities. [20:00 - end ] More on Mrs. King situation and civil rights in Mississippi. Explanation of freedom riders, more about what he was working on while staying with Mrs. King. For the election of the mayor and five councilmen, there were too many African American candidates for the number of positions available, so O'Dwyer had to convince two candidates to drop out so that the African American vote would not be split. One did rather easily, but a local minister was much more difficult to convince.First elected African American mayor in Sunflower (did not happen during that election). (Box 4, Cd 1, Track 2, Box 3, Box 1, Cassette 1)
    [08:48] We're just establishing here that Mr. O'Dwyer did not belong to a specific organization at that time. It's just a matter of record.
    [12:04] Was this priest of a local parish? That was his function? He was a local parish priest?
    [12:26] And they worked alone - these parish priests?
    [13:01] Am I correct in assuming when you say that out of the 125 priests in Mississippi 75 of them were from Ireland? Do you know the reason why?
    [13:34] So they actually then imported the priests from Ireland?
    [13:57] And were these priests, these Irish priests, were they volunteers to this community?
    Questions RE: Trip to Sunflower, MS with the purpose of convincing African Americans that voting works. Stayed in the home of Mrs. King, an African American woman whose house was firebombed because she accommodated freedom riders. His stay with her and more on her situation.
    [18:23] By what means did you get these accommodations? What network was working for you then?
    [19:48] This is in the north of Mississippi now? Where you were staying with her?
    [23:01] Did you sleep well that night?
    [27:57] What type of trouble? Specifically?
    [29:32] Did you meet with a lot of opposition in those days?
    [29:41] I mean something outright - that you were told to go home, stay out of our state, anything in that…?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc; [00:00 - 10:00] Case in Alligator, MS where O'Dwyer advised a group of young African Americans how to conduct themselves in court when they were being charged with ?? protest? Negotiations with Butler, the man in charge. [10:00 - 20:00] More on civil rights in the South. Practicalities of practicing law away from own office. [20:00 - end] More on Hazard case. Four of the eight defendants were illiterate. Attempt to transfer case to Lexington. One of the miners became a preacher during trial. Discussion of Baptist preachers. Discusses Simpson as his campaign manager for 1968 campaign to become a U.S. Senator. (Box 4, Cd 2, Track 1, Box 1, Cassette 2, Box 3)
    [2:40] But these young people must have been very frightened. They didn't? I was going to ask how you allayed their fears, but…?
    [3:04] It seemed to be maybe more of an adventure to them?
    [10:21] When you were representing, defending people, down in Mississippi, who did your paperwork?
    [10:41] Mostly done in New York then?
    [10:57] But what if you had to make various changes and stuff?
    [11:12] Nobody would actually say, "Come in - use my office" while you were there. There was no such thing as that?
    Questions RE: O'Dwyer's experiences as a child in Ireland during the Black and Tan/War of Independence.
    [11:47] Where were your training grounds to do this kind of work and where did your desire come from within you?
    [12:42] How old were you at that time?
    Questions RE: Case of eight unemployed white miners charged with blowing up the entrance to a mine in Hazard, Kentucky. Work with Dan Jack Coombs, the only lawyer in Kentucky who would take the case. Attitude of local judge.
    [24:45] Do you know what denomination the preacher was?
    [26:20] These young boys - their illiteracy was perpetuated over time then. You have mentioned before that they were the result of settlers that had settled a long time ago. Is that correct?
    [26:36] And so they continued with this illiterate form throughout the age - even as recently as the seventies?
    [27:02] Do you know what prevented them from getting an education? Were there just not enough schools in that area?
    [27:29] Just following the Bible and listening to the local preacher would be enough?
    [28:14] He was your campaign manager when you were running for which office?
    [28:50] Did you feel that these businesses - your clients - that they were, the illiterate ones particularly, were they content with their lives other than this situation that came about? Did they seem like they were happy people?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990, Feb 6, 1990; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Hazard case. How defendants were caught. Kept in touch with defendants for many years.History of anti-Semitism in Russia, Russian Revolution, MarxismVolunteered to go to Russia with Percy Sutton to assess the civil rights situation in 1972-73. [10:00 - 20:00] More on experiences in Russia. Being followed by the KGB. Visit to the home of an unemployed professor, where only his 14-year-old son spoke any English. Using a toy to communicate with the family. [20:00 - end] Had to go to Kiev to get the facts of a case in which a man named Feldman had applied for a visa to Israel or the United States. He was charged with hooliganism (similar to disorderly conduct) after making a woman drop a cake she was carrying by accidentally bumping into her.O'Dwyer had found a written record of the case so that they could bring it to light as an example of a violation of civil rights.Attempt to go to Kiev. Description of airport and plane not leaving. Going to see movie in Moscow. (Box 1, Cassette 2, Box 3, Cd 2, Track 2, Box 4)
    [12:57] Did you meet any Jewish people in Russia at that time who were accomplished and educated?
    [15:44] What did you feel at that time?
    [16:08] Whose home was this?
    [16:22] Do you remember what school he was working at?
    [18:10] This is with the young boy? So that nothing could be reported or retained? You had to keep everything in your minds?
    [18:27] It was just a toy here - my children have those.
    [18:38] Had you brought that with you or was that supplied to you in Russia?
    [18:55] Is it possible that that was used as a tool in school for the children similar to the old fashioned slate? And also save paper?
    [20:36] Did they actually call it hooliganism?
    [21:45] Who told you this? Did Mr. Feldman? You never met him?
    [21:58] You never met him because he had this brush with this woman and…?
    [22:41] What was his profession? Do you recall?
    [23:29] Was it from that record that you found out what happened to him or were you told by his relatives as well?
    [28:59] So your friend had no way of knowing exactly why you weren't going to Kiev but just that word came back, "There's no plane going to Kiev."
    [29:42] The one and only cinema in Moscow?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 6 February 1990 [Partial transcript], Feb 6, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 October 1990, Oct 17, 1990; 1 master cassette, 1 master compact disc, 1 access compact disc; [00:00 - 10:00] Russia c. 1972 - O'Dwyer in Moscow gathering whatever information he can before he has to leave the country. Discussion of Jewish religious practices. [10:00 - 20:00] Story about being invited to speak at a church in Harlem when running for City Council.Discussion of J. Raymond Jones, who later became the leader of Tammany Hall - why African Americans in Harlem were Republican and not Democrats at that time.Reflects on trip to Russia - met Sutton, O'Dwyer had just been elected on the reform ticket as President of the New York City Council. City Council years - relationship with mayor, political split of Council. [20:00 - end ] More on City Council: chain of power; financial problems when the bank did not renew the City's credit, proposal to create municipal committee headed by industry people that would have to approve budget in order for it to pass. O'Dwyer believed it took away the power from the people because the committee was not elected.Changes in New York City from when O'Dwyer first arrived to when he became President of City Council, Irish Americans' situations. (Box 1, Cassette 3, Box 3, Cd 3, Track 1, Box 4)
    [07:09] So, actually, the only thing they knew about their heritage and everything would have been from what the old people would have told them. But they couldn't practice it or…?
    [07:23] They held a lot back?
    [07:53] So, actually mingling in with the rest of society?
    [08:33] Was there a restriction on the age limit? You said only the older people were going to the synagogue?
    [08:40] So it was just a known thing. You were a certain age at a certain time, you could go and practice, but if you weren't, stay away?
    [09:02] So there was no underground religion at all going on there?
    [12:16 ] Do you recall who this sponsor person was?
    [12:23] What was his political affiliation at the time?